Charles Coleman Papers, 1944-1986 SC 9
Archives of African American Music and Culture
Charles Coleman Papers
1944-1986
Archives of African American Music and Culture
Coleman, Charles, Jr. (Charles DeWitt), 1929-1991
SC 9
1 document case 0.21 linear feet
This collection consists of printed and manuscript scores of music by Charles Coleman, including sacred and secular choral works, as well as ephemeral materials related to the composer.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series:
Series 1: Manuscript Scores
Series 2: Printed Scores
Series 3: Ephemera
Biographical / Historical
Charles DeWitt Coleman, Jr. was born in Detroit, Michigan on January 29, 1929. He was the founder and director of the Coleman Studio of Music, later known as the Northwestern School of Music, and a member of the Artists Bureau of the National Assocation of Negro Musicians. Coleman was a pupil of Robert Nolan at the Robert Nolan School of Music, August Maekelberghe, Robert Cato, and Virgil Fox, and received his Bachelor of Music degree from Wayne State University in 1954. He later studied with reknowned organist and composer Marcel Dupre from Paris, France and European piano pedagogy and organ with Lode Van Dessel of the Palestrina Institute. He conducted at many schools in the Detroit Public School System, as well as various church ensembles of various ages and faiths, and was awarded the degree A.A.G.O. by the American Guild of Organists in 1955.
Access Restrictions
Use of time-based media materials (audio and video) may require production of listening or viewing copies.
Access to streaming audio, moving image, and full resolution digital image materials may currently be restricted to researchers who can authenticate with an IU account or who are physically present on campus. Remote streaming to individual researchers may be allowed with the completion of applicable forms.
For further information about access to online audiovisual materials, contact AAAMC staff at aaamc@indiana.edu.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Ronald F. Coleman in 1998.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the collection is made up of manuscript scores of works by Coleman, as well as printed scores of some of his music. Materials are individually sleeved in clear plastic with title printed on label. Works are arranged alphabetically within series.
Music by African American composers; African American composers
- 1. Manuscript Scores, 1944-1963; 23 works; 24 manuscript scores
  - African Dance / [by Charles Coleman], 1 ms. condensed score 2 pages; 31 cm. Holograph sketch, in pencil. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Dance No. 1 [for piano] / [by] Chas. D. Coleman, 1944; 1 Manuscript Score (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General
    Note
    Markings in red pencil, including deletion of word "American" in title.
  - Go Down Moses [for mixed voices] / by Coleman, 1952; 1 Manuscript Score (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hear Our Prayer; Te Deum [for mixed voices], 1951; 1 Manuscript Score (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - John Kennedy [for mixed voices and piano] / words and music by Charles Coleman (two copies), 1963; 2 Manuscript Score (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Kyrie Eleison [for solo voices or chorus (SAB) and piano] / C. Coleman., 1 Manuscript Score (Box 1, Folder 2)
    On title page: "Music 301."
  - Lead Kindly Light [for mixed voices] / [arranged by?] Charles Coleman., 1 Manuscript Score (Box 1, Folder 2)
    On title page: John Newman, 1801-1890.
  - The Lord's Prayer [for mixed voices] / [by] C. D. Coleman, [19]55; 1 Manuscript Score (Box 1, Folder 2)
    At bottom of page: To the Excelsior Choir of the Tabernacle Baptist Church.
  - Minuet [for piano] / [by] Chas. D. Coleman, 1944; 1 Manuscript Score (Box 1, Folder 2)
    At top of title page: Dedicated to the Progressive Miss Gloria Taylor.
  - Mu Delta Mu [for solo? voice and piano] / [by] Charles D. Coleman, 1946; 1 Manuscript Score (Box 1, Folder 2)
    At top of title page: Sept. 20, 1946.
  - Nocturne [for piano] / [by Charles Coleman]., 1 Manuscript Score (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The 100th Psalm [for chorus (SATB) and organ] / [by] C. Coleman., 1 Manuscript Score (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Prelude to Life [for unspecified treble instrument and piano or organ] / [by Charles Coleman]., 1 Manuscript Score (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Title added in green ink. At end: Aug. 4.
  - Practice [for piano] / [by Charles Coleman]., 1 Manuscript Score (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rise Up O Men of God [arr. for mixed voices and piano] / [by] Charles Coleman., 1 Manuscript Score (Box 1, Folder 3)
    At top of title page: Wm. [Merrill?]-1867.
  - Show Me Thy Way [for mixed voices] / [by Charles] Coleman, 1951; 1 Manuscript Score (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Take Up Thy Cross "Wareham" [for high voice] / [by] C. Coleman, 1958; 1 ms. part 1 page; 29 cm. Holograph sketch, ink over mimeograph copy. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    At bottom of page: "Oct. 19, 1958 / Tabernacle Baptist Church / C. Coleman".
  - Theme: Small Town USA; Story Lady Theme: Orient [for piano] / [arr.? by Charles Coleman]., 1 Manuscript Score (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - To Joyce [for piano] / [by] Chas. Coleman, 1943; 2 Manuscript Score (Box 1, Folder 4)
    On verso: To Joyce composition written 1943 Detroit dedicated to Miss Joyce Taylor By Charles D. Coleman, composer.
  - Tone Row [for piano]., 1 Manuscript Score (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Notes about various composers on verso.
  - Two Part Invention Music [for piano] / [by?] C. Coleman., 1 Manuscript Score (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - [Untitled excerpt, for mixed high voices] / [by Charles Coleman], 1956; 1 Manuscript Score (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Page is numbered as pg. 2.
    At end of score: For the Tabernacle Women's Chorus / April 13th 1956 / Detroit, Mich.
  - Violin Duo [for 2 violins] / [by] C. Coleman, 1957; 1 Manuscript Score (Box 1, Folder 4)
    At end of score: Chares [sic] Coleman, Jan. 1957 / University of Michigan.
- 2. Printed Scores, 1964-1986; 11 works; 18 printed scores
  - Alleluia / Charles D. Coleman. Detroit: Northwestern School of Music Press, 1976; 1 Score (Box 1, Folder 5)
    For mixed voices (SATB) with optional piano accompaniment.
  - Be Thou Faithful Unto Death / Charles D. Coleman. Detroit: Northwestern School of Music Press, 1986; 1 Score (Box 1, Folder 5)
    For mixed voices (SSAATTBB) and piano.
    At head of title page: For the annual convention of the N.A.N.M., Aug. 16-23, 1953 / Dr. Roscoe R. Polin, President / First performance: Dett Choral Club of Indianapolis, Ind.
  - Blest Be the Tie / Charles D. Coleman. Detroit: Northwestern School of Music Press, 1977; 1 Score (Box 1, Folder 5)
    For mixed voices and piano.
    At head of title page: For the Detroit Public Library Hackley Memorial Concert, March 10, 1958; First performance: Excelsior Choir.
  - The Christmas Song / Charles D. Coleman, Nov. '49. Detroit: Northwestern School of Music Press, 1985; 2 Score (Box 1, Folder 5)
    For mixed voices (SATB); piano accompaniment for rehearsal only.
  - Impromptu / Charles Coleman. Detroit: Northwestern School of Music Press, 1977; 4 Score (Box 1, Folder 5)
    For organ, pedals alone.
  - Let Us Break Bread: Communion Spiritual / arranged by Charles D. Coleman. Detroit: Northwestern School of Music Press, 1976; 1 Score (Box 1, Folder 5)
    For mixed voices (SATB).
  - The Lord's Prayer / Charles D. Coleman. Detroit: Northwestern School of Music Press, 1964; 3 Score (Box 1, Folder 6)
    For mixed voices (SATB) and piano.
  - O Perfect Love / Charles D. Coleman, and [words by?] Dorothy Gurney. Detroit: Northwestern School of Music Press, 1977; 1 Score (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Top of title page: For Brazeal W. Dennard and his Bride Murtis August 26th 1959.
  - O Perfect Love / Charles D. Coleman and [words by?] Dorothy Gurney. Detroit: Northwestern School of Music Press, [1977?]; 1 Score (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Pages 2 and 3 are missing. Arranged for high voices and piano.
  - Praise to the Lord / Charles Coleman '74. Detroit: Northwestern School of Music Press, 1977; 1 Score (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Trumpet part on verso, page 17. For 2 trumpets, mixed voices (SATB), and organ.
    At head of title page: For Brazeal Dennard and the North Western Hi Choir.
  - Seeking for That City / arranged by Charles Coleman. Detroit: Northwestern School of Music Press, 1977; 1 Score (Box 1, Folder 6)
    For soprano solo, mixed voices, and piano.
  - Sonata No. 1: for organ / Charles D. Coleman. Detroit: Northwestern School of Music Press, 1979; 1 Score (Box 1, Folder 6)
    At head of title page: Dedicated to Dr. Eugene Hancock.
- 3. Ephemera, undated.
  - Ephemeral Materials, undated., 1 photograph in color, Northwestern School of Music, Dance and Drama brochure, biographical materials, Violin Duo program notes (1957). (Box 1, Folder 7)